Okay, today's דף daf is ק"י, Kuf Yud, מנחות Menachos 110. With
this, we finish the פרק, perek, finish the מסכת, masechet, very exciting,
and we are in the middle of a discussion of בית חוניו,
Beit Chonyo, the house, the temple of Onias, which was built in
Egypt. According to the גמרא, Gemara, it was in Alexandria, but actually
it was in a different part of the Nile Delta called the
land of Onias. And one of the descendants or the son of
שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzadik, and the question was whether it was a
house of עבודה זרה avodah zarah or a house of worship to
God. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said it was a house of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it was a
house of worship to God, still it was forbidden because it was
שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, bringing קרבנות korbanot outside of the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, but still better than עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So, and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda quoted a פסוק pasuk from ישעיהו Yeshayahu that
said, ביום
ההוא יהיה מזבח לה' בתוך ארץ מצרים ומצבה אצל גבולה לה', Ba'yom
hahu yiheyeh mizbe'ach l'Hashem b'toch eretz Mitzrayim u'matzeva etzel gevulah l'Hashem, prophesying
that there will be an altar to God in the land of
Egypt. So that seems to be nice to read that as a
describing the בית חוניו Beit Chonyo and evidence that it was for
serving God. So the גמרא Gemara said, "What does רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir do with that פסוק?" pasuk? So it says, "Well, no, he
reads that פסוק pasuk and the פסוק pasuk right before it, that
it's talking about the time of חזקיהו Chizkiyahu and when they won
the battle over סנחריב, Sancheriv, the foreign princes that were in the
camp, he made them swear that they would not be עובדי עבודה
זרה. ovdei avodah zarah. And when they went back to Egypt, they
actually worshiped God." And we pick up at the top of ק"י
Kuf Yud with the end of that point. הלכו לאלכסנדריה של מצרים
ובנו מזבח והעלו עליו לשם שמים, Halchu l'Alexandria shel Mitzrayim u'vanu mizbe'ach
v'he'elu alav l'shem shamayim, so these princes went to
Alexandria and they built an
altar and they offered on it to God, so it is not
referring to the house of חוניו Chonyo but to a completely different
historical event. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says, ביום ההוא יהיה
מזבח לה' בתוך ארץ מצרים. Ba'yom hahu yiheyeh mizbe'ach l'Hashem b'toch eretz
Mitzrayim. Okay, so that is how רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir deals with
that פסוק. pasuk. Now,
עיר ההרס יאמר לאחת מהן, Ir HaHeres ye'amer l'achat mehen, the city
of destruction will be said about one of them. So that was
the פסוק pasuk right before it. The whole פסוק pasuk is, this
is ישעיהו י"ט י"ח, Yeshayahu Yud Tes Yud Chet, ביום ההוא יהיו
חמש ערים בארץ מצרים מדברות שפת כנען, Ba'yom hahu yiheyu chamesh arim
b'eretz Mitzrayim medabrot sfat Kna'an, there will be five cities speaking the
land of כנען, Kna'an, meaning the language of the land of כנען,
Kna'an, Hebrew, so here being read by רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir as
these five kings or princes who brought this back with them, could
be read to be referring again to בית חוניו Beit Chonyo and
the area around it. And the end of that פסוק pasuk is,
ונשבעות לה' צבאות עיר ההרס יאמר לאחת מהן, v'nishba'ot l'Hashem Tzeva'ot Ir
HaHeres ye'amer l'achat mehen, a city of destruction will be said to
one of them. So what does that mean, the city of destruction?
מאי עיר ההרס יאמר לאחת? Mai Ir HaHeres ye'amer l'achat? כדמתרגם רב
יוסף, K'targum Rav Yosef, like רב יוסף Rav Yosef translates it, קרתי
דבית שמש דעתיד למיחרב איתאמר דהיא חדא מנהון, Kartei d'Beis Shemesh d'atid
l'michrav it'amar dehi chada mi'hon, the city of
בית שמש Beis Shemesh that in the end will be destroyed,
it will be said that it was one of them. So is
he talking about the בית שמש Beis Shemesh that is in Israel?
Not clear, because this is about ארץ מצרים, eretz Mitzrayim, so apparently
some other city called the House of the Sun. So חרס, heres,
as we'll see, there's one פסוק pasuk that the word חרס heres
seems to mean sun. So the City of Sun, the City of
Destruction will be said to one of them. So
it doesn't really
add much, but just give some historical context. What does it mean
one of them will be said a
City of Destruction? So he's saying, "No, there'll be a city of
the sun that will be destroyed and will be called the City
of Destruction." Okay, so וממאי דעיר ההרס לישנא דשמשא הוא? U'mimai d'Ir
HaHeres lishana d'shimsha hu? Where do you get this idea that the
city of חרס heres means the city of the sun? דכתיב האומר
לחרס ולא יזרח, De'chtiv h'omer l'cheres v'lo yizrach, חרס, cheres, חרס, heres,
both like a guttural
sound, God speaks to the חרס cheres and it will not shine
forth. So in the context, it's איוב, Iyov, there are so many
difficult and unusual words in איוב, Iyov, but in context, it seems
that that means sun. So that's how we're able to interpret that
פסוק. pasuk. I should mention that in the Septuagint, which is the
Greek translation,
they translate the word עיר ההרס, Ir HaHeres, I believe, as like
the City of Splendor or something of that nature. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. הביאי בני מרחוק ובנותי מקצה הארץ. Habii
vanay merachok u'vnotai miktzei ha'aretz.
So since we're talking about exile and about
the what was happening with the Jews even in Egypt and how
they were worshiping God, that seems to be the reason now that
we're going to quote פסוקים pesukim that are going to speak about
Jews that are spread out. Okay, so the verse says, "Bring my
sons from far away and my daughters from the edges of the
land." So הביאי בני מרחוק, Habii vanay merachok, what does that mean
"my sons from far away"? Why the distinction between sons and daughters?
אמר רב הונא אלו גלויות שבבבל, Amar Rav Huna elu galuyot she'be'vavel,
these are the exiles
in Babylon. which probably means that because so many of the תלמידי
חכמים Talmidei Chachamim and so much of the primary Jewish settlement was
in בבל, Bavel, and so therefore the Jews that are in בבל,
Bavel,
they're doing okay, and that's where they're going to come back in
the time of the קיבוץ גלויות, Kibbutz Galuyot, but דעתם מיושבת עליהם.
daatam meyushevet aleihem. ובנותיי מקצה הארץ, uvenotai miketze haaretz, my daughters from
the edges of the land, אלו גלויות ששאר ארצות, elu galuyot sheshaar
aratzot, those are the Jews exiled in other lands, שאין דעתם מיושבת
עליהם, sheein daatam meyushevet aleihem, that they don't have it so well,
they don't have calmness, they don't have tranquility, they don't have peace
of mind.
So obviously here some assumption that I don't know, רש"י, Rashi, if
you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says sons are דעתן מיושבת
daatan meyushevet more than daughters. Again, what exactly does that mean, what's
the גמרא Gemara assuming? It's saying like men are more rational, women
are more emotional. I don't know what the גמרא Gemara is intending
by that. But anyway, that's how it is reading this. Okay. שאין
דעתם מיושבת עליהם. sheein daatam meyushevet aleihem. I think I might have
skipped the word.
בבל שדעתן מיושבת עליהם כבנים. Bavel shedaatan meyushevet aleihem kevanim. In בבל
Bavel they have their mind settled like sons. ובנותיי מקצה הארץ אלו
גלויות ששאר ארצות שאין דעתן מיושבת עליהם כבנות. uvenotai miketze haaretz elu
galuyot sheshaar aratzot sheein daatan meyushevet aleihem kevanot. The other lands that
it's not settled like daughters. Alright. אמר רבי אבא בר רב יצחק
אמר רב חסדא ואמרי לה אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rabbi
Abba bar Rav Yitzchak amar Rav Chisda veamri lah amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, so different traditions of who said this. Again, talking
about the exiles and
the reality of the lands away from ישראל. Yisrael. And said the
following. מצור ועד קרטיגי, Mitzor vead Kartigi, קרטיגגי, Kartigigi, from Tyre till
Carthage, מכירין ישראל ואת אביהם שבשמים. makirin Yisrael veet avihem shebashamayim. So
this now we're not even talking about, it's related to where the
Jews have gone into exile, but it's the focus is on the
non-Jews. From Tyre to Carthage, they recognize the Jewish people and they
recognize their father in heaven. Presumably because they recognize the Jewish people,
therefore they
understand the idea of a single God and that is what the
Jewish people are, bring to the world. So they recognize that, whether
they believe in it or worship that single God, it's possible that
that's what it means. If רש"י Rashi says that, ואביהם שבשמים, veavihem
shebashamayim, שמאמינים
בהקדוש
ברוך הוא, shemaaminim beHakadosh Baruch Hu, they affirm their belief in God
and
they're not in עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But at least it's מכירין.
makirin. They understand what the Jews represent and their faith and the
idea of a single God. ומצור כלפי מערב, uMitzor klapei maarav, but
from Tyre to the west, ומקרטיגגי כלפי מזרח, umiKartigigi klapei mizrach, and
from Carthage to the east, אין מכירין את ישראל ולא את אביהם
שבשמים. ein makirin et Yisrael velo et avihem shebashamayim. They don't recognize
the Jewish people, meaning presumably so the Jewish people had not, weren't
exiled there and therefore the world doesn't know of the Jewish people
and presumably as a result don't recognize their father in heaven, don't
understand
what the Jewish people represent to the world and what they brought
to the world, the understanding of the belief in a single God.
Now I have to tell you that I find I don't understand
the directions here, the map that they're drawing. Because Carthage is to
the west of ישראל, Yisrael, right? If you move west from ישראל
Yisrael along the Mediterranean, you basically hit like Turkey, Greece, Italy, Sicily,
and then Carthage is in Tunis, there at the tip of Africa.
It's way to the west of ישראל. Yisrael. So it should have
said
from Carthage to the east and from Tyre to the west, right?
In that and there they don't recognize ישראל. Yisrael. But this is
pointing from Tyre to the west and Carthage to the east is
actually that is between Carthage and Tyre. So I looked at all
the different manuscripts of this דף, daf, all the ancient manuscripts that
we have, ancient, whatever medieval, and hoping that one of them would
have the directions reversed, but it does not. So I really don't
understand what sense this makes in terms of the east-west should be
reversed. Anyway, but that is the point. So presumably ישראל Yisrael has
been exiled throughout that lands around the Mediterranean and that's had that
impact. But beyond that they don't know ישראל, Yisrael, they don't know
the idea of a single God. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, first wide line, end of the first wide line. איתיביה
רב שימי בר חייא לרב. Eitiveih Rav Shimi bar Chiya leRav. So
רב שימי בר חייא Rav Shimi bar Chiya challenges this רב Rav
and the statement of that רב Rav said. Here a פסוק pasuk
says ממזרח שמש ועד מבואו, mimizrach shemesh vead mevoo, from the raising
of from the shining of the sun until its setting, meaning from
the east to the west, גדול שמי בגוים, gadol shemi bagoyim, my
name is great among the nations,
ובכל מקום מוקטר מוגש לשמי, uvechol makom muktar mugash lishmi, something is
incense being burnt and offered in my name, and a pure מנחה.
mincha. So it says like it sounds like everywhere in the world
they recognize God. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב Rav said
to
שימיא, Shimiya, what שימיא? Shimiya? Like that's a question worthy of you?
No, what it means is that my name is great דקרו ליה
אלהא דאלהיא. d'karai lei Elaha d'Alahaya. They call God the God of
Gods. But they don't worship him, they worship עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
But that's strange, it's not clear immediately what the answer is because
the earlier statement was not whether the nations worship God or worship
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, is whether they are מכירים makirim אביהם שבשמים.
avihem shebashamayim. Do they recognize? So if they're calling God the God
of Gods, even if they believe that there are gods underneath, why
isn't that מכירים makirim אביהם שבשמים? avihem shebashamayim? So the מהרש"א Maharsha
explains that part of recognizing God through the Jewish people is recognizing
not only that a supreme single God exists, but also recognizing that
God has השגחה פרטית, hashgacha pratis, that God is involved in history
and involved in our lives. So outside there, when they don't and
maybe that's a little bit evoked by the word אביהם שבשמים, avihem
shebashamayim, Father, one who cares about us. So outside they might recognize
the idea of an all-powerful God, they worship the gods underneath, but
they recognize an all-powerful God, but it's not אביהם שבשמים. avihem shebashamayim.
It's not the God of the Jewish experience of השגחה פרטית. hashgacha
pratis. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ובכל מקום,
uv'chol makom, so now we're going to interpret the end of the
פסוק. passuk. ובכל מקום מקטר מגש לשמי, uv'chol makom muktar mugash lishmi,
in every place it is incense is offered up, offered in my
name. ובכל מקום סלקא דעתך? uv'chol makom salka daitach? In every place?
What does that mean? They're not offering worshiping God everywhere. So אמר
רבי שמעון בר נחמני amar Rabbi Shimon bar Nachmani and also it's
not if we're talking about Jews worshiping God, it can't be outside
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So אמר רבי שמעון בר נחמני אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Shimon bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yochanan יונתן, Yonatan,
excuse me, אלו תלמידי חכמים העוסקים בתורה בכל מקום. elu talmidei chachamim
ha'oskim baTorah b'chol makom.
No, this means תורה Torah sages that learn תורה Torah in every
place. מעלה אני עליהם כאילו מקטירים ומגישים לשמי. ma'aleh ani aleihem k'ilu
maktirim umagishim lishmi. It's like they are burning incense and offering up
to me. So now, very appropriate for the end of מנחות, Menachos,
speaking about we don't have קרבנות, korbanos, right, זבחים Zevachim ומנחות u'Menachos
if you think about that's the big focus on קרבנות, korbanos, then
we're going to get to חולין, Chullin, which is going to be
about non-sanctified שחיטה. shechita. But here we've just done, there's going to
be more left to cut but we've just done the two major
מסכתות masechtot about קרבנות. korbanos. We don't have קרבנות. korbanos. So where
does that leave us? So the statement here is that no, when
you're learning תורה Torah it's like you are offering
קרבנות. korbanos. כאילו מקטירים ומגישים לשמי. k'ilu maktirim umagishim lishmi. Now one
thing I might sort- well let's hold on. So that's the first
statement, that that's what it means in all places and in that
way תורה Torah is more powerful because you're able to because then
it happens everywhere, not just in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and
it counts
equal to the offering of the
קרבן. korban. לשמי. lishmi. ומנחה טהורה, umincha tehorah, now what does the
end of the פסוק passuk mean? The pure מנחה. mincha. זה הלומד
תורה בטהרה. zeh ha-lomed Torah b'taharah. That is somebody who learns תורה
Torah in purity. To טהורה, tahora, how? נושא אשה ואחר כך לומד
תורה. nosei isha v'achar kach lomed Torah. First you get married and
then you learn תורה Torah because then a person is not distracted
by sexual
thoughts and is able to learn תורה Torah totally focused with pure
thoughts.
Alright, we're going to continue on this theme that learning תורה Torah
counts as offering קרבן. korban. שיר המעלות, shir ha-Ma'alot, the song of
ascent, הנה ברכו את ה' כל עבדי ה' העומדים בבית ה' בלילות,
hinei barchu et Hashem kol avdei Hashem ha'omdim b'veit Hashem baleilot, who
stands in the house of God at night. בלילות? baleilot? What do
you mean at night? You don't do קרבנות korbanos at night.
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, back to תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim,
these are the תורה Torah sages העוסקים בתורה בלילה. ha-oskim baTorah balaila.
They learn תורה Torah at night. מעלה עליהם הכתוב כאילו עוסקים בעבודה.
ma'aleh aleihem hakatuv k'ilu oskim ba'avodah. It's like they are involving themselves
in the temple worship. And again, it is more expansive, you can
learn תורה Torah any place, not just in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. You can learn תורה Torah at night, not just like in-
not קרבנות korbanos which are only in the day. So in a
way it's expanding the קדושה kedusha and the connection to God as,
but it's framed as כאילו מקריב קרבן. k'ilu makriv korban. לעולם
זאת על ישראל.
l'olam zot
al Yisrael. This is another פסוק. passuk. The full פסוק passuk is
the following: הנני בונה בית לשם ה' אלקי. hineni boneh bayit l'shem
Hashem Elokai. This is in דברי הימים divrei HaYamim from שלמה. Shlomo.
להקדיש לו, l'hakdish lo, I'm building a house to God and להקטיר
לפניו קטרת סמים, l'haktir l'fanav ketoret samim, to sanctify it, to offer
incense, ומערכת תמיד, u'ma'arechet tamid, and the fire, ועולות לבוקר ולערב, v'olot
laboker v'la'erev, and burnt offerings morning and evening. לשבתות ולחדשים ולמועדי ה'
אלקינו לעולם זאת על ישראל. l'shabbatot v'lchodashim ulmoadei Hashem Elokeinu l'olam zot
al Yisrael. This is forever over ישראל. Yisrael. So אמר רבי- amar
Rabbi so is it really forever? There's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
now. It didn't last forever. אמר רב גידל אמר רב, amar Rav
Gidel amar Rav, זה מזבח בנוי ומיכאל שר הגדול עומד ומקריב עליו
קרבן. zeh mizbe'ach banui u'Michael sar hagadol omeid umakriv alav korban. Yes,
even without the physical בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash you have a supernal
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash up in heaven.
And therefore there is always an offering that is being done, okay,
that the great angel מיכאל Michael is offering קרבנות korbanot to God
up in heaven. Which is very interesting, why does God need angels
offering קרבנות? korbanot? Certainly puts the whole idea of קרבנות korbanot in
some like this metaphysical power which requires, you know, which is like
like somehow feeds the spiritual energy of the world, and therefore what
we do down here is parallel to up there, and even when
there is no בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash it's taking place up there.
So that's a very like powerful image about what the what קרבנות
korbanot do. I mean not specific about what קרבנות korbanot but like
how necessary they are to like the spiritual health of the world.
We'll see how the גמרא Gemara will contrast that a little bit
after the next
משנה. Mishnah. Okay, רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar אלו תלמידי חכמים
עוסקים בהלכות עבודה. elu talmidei chachamim oskim behilchot avodah. So no, not
actual something about the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but those are תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim that learn the laws of the worship of the
temple. מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו נבנה מקדש בימיהם. Maaleh alav hakatuv k'ilu
nivneh mikdash beyameihem. It's like the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is built,
and therefore that is the לעולם. le'olam. So this goes back to
the similar point as before, right? So now תורה Torah and the
ability to worship through תורה Torah is all places, not day and
and night, and after even when there's no בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
In all these ways transcending the limits of the actual עבודה avodah
in the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish מאי דכתיב
mai d'chtiv זאת התורה לעולה למנחה ולחטאת ולאשם, Zot HaTorah l'olah laminchah
v'lachatat v'la'asham, okay, which is, you know, the way the תורה Torah
sort of wraps up, you know, in צו Tzav after it lays
out all of the basic parameters and מצוות mitzvot of the
קרבנות. korbanot. To tell you, this is the תורה Torah for, you
know, burnt offering and the מנחה minchah and the sin offering and
the אשם, asham, the other type of sin offering. To teach you
זאת התורה, Zot HaTorah, כל העוסק בתורה כאילו הקריב עולה מנחה חטאת
ואשם. kol ha'osek baTorah k'ilu hikriv olah minchah chatat v'asham. If זאת
התורה, Zot HaTorah, if you learn the תורה, Torah, it's like you
offered all these sacrifices. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, but now רבא Rava
says slightly differently. האי לעולה למנחה, Hai l'olah laminchah, it shouldn't have
said for the עולה, olah, for the מנחה. minchah. עולה ומנחה מיבעי.
Olah u'minchah mi'ba'ei. It should have said like תורת עולה, torat olah,
תורת מנחה. torat minchah. What is לעולה ולמנחה? la'olah v'laminchah? אלא אמר
רבא Ela amar Rava כל
העוסק בתורה אינו צריך לא עולה ולא מנחה ולא חטאת ולא אשם.
kol ha'osek baTorah eino tzarich lo olah v'lo minchah v'lo chatat v'lo
asham. What it's coming to tell you is that if you learn
תורה Torah you don't need an עולה, olah, a חטאת, chatat, a
מנחה, minchah, and an אשם. asham. Now, how is that different than
what was said before? Okay, and what what is he reading differently
in the פסוק? pasuk? So רש"י Rashi just says the ל la
means this תורה Torah counts equivalent to, you know, an עולה, olah,
a מנחה, minchah, etc., so you don't need the actual thing. And
then it's almost identical to what was said before, which is that
it counts as if you offered those things up. You know, the
מהרש"א Maharsha tries to explain a slight difference by saying no, you
know, to offer up a חטאת chatat means you sinned and now
you owe a חטאת. chatat. If this is you don't need a
חטאת, chatat, it's telling you that the learning of תורה Torah prevents
you from sinning, so we'll avoid the need for these in the
future. I actually think it's saying something different, and also the grammatical
point. לעולה, La'olah, you know, in in it's clear that certainly
in like the Hebrew in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in the
משנה, Mishnah, לא la could mean not. I think it's that way
in Arabic as well, not just
לא. lo. Okay, so when you get that in a דרש drash
sometimes, if somebody says לא la X, it's understood to mean not
X. So what he is reading is זאת התורה, Zot HaTorah, this
is the תורה, Torah, לעולה, la'olah, you don't need an
עולה, olah, למנחה, la minchah, you don't need a מנחה. minchah. And
I think it's saying something besides that grammatical point, different than what
was said before. Before, it's holding up the עבודה avodah in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as the ideal, so much to the point
that there was even this whole thing about מיכאל Michael offering up
in heaven.
But and תורה Torah just is as if you did it. It
might have a power that it transcends limitations, but it's as if
you did the קרבנות, korbanot, the קרבנות korbanot are, you know, the
model, are the ideal. רבא Rava is saying, no, תורה, Torah, if
you learn תורה, Torah, you don't need קרבנות. korbanot. They're completely different
paths. תורה Torah is one way to serve God, קרבנות korbanot is
another. תורה Torah counts, you know, for its own value, you know,
and it's just as good, maybe even better than קרבנות. korbanot. It's
not you don't need קרבנות korbanot if you're learning תורה. Torah. It's
a very different type of a statement.
Okay, so okay, אמר רבי יצחק amar Rabbi Yitzchak מאי דכתיב mai
d'chtiv זאת תורת החטאת וזאת תורת האשם, Zot torat hachatat v'zot torat
ha'asham, this is the תורה Torah of the חטאת, chatat, the תורה
Torah of the אשם. asham. Again, תורה, Torah, but it's בסמיכות bismichut
with the word חטאת chatat and אשם. asham. To tell you, כל
העוסק בתורת חטאת כאילו הקריב חטאת, kol ha'osek betorat chatat k'ilu hikriv
chatat, וכל העוסק בתורת אשם כאילו הקריב אשם. v'kol ha'osek betorat asham
k'ilu hikriv asham. If you learn the law of a
חטאת... chatat... So that seems pretty much identical to what we were
saying before. If you learn תורה Torah *Torah* it's like you did
the עבודה avodah, *avodah*, but the מהרש"א *Maharsha* points out there's a
subtle difference here because before it was making the statement if you
learn תורה Torah *Torah*, any תורה *Torah*, you know you learn סוכה
*Sukkah* it's like you offered קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. It's a way of
serving God, you know, the same way קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* is a
way of serving God, this is like you offered קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*,
not any specific קרבן korban *korban*, you know, but it's sort of
similar to the way קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* are, has the same efficacy
and is working in a similar track. Here it's very much specifically
not just generally תורה *Torah* is like you did עבודה *avodah*, but
the תורה *Torah* of a חטאת *chatat* counts as a חטאת *chatat*.
When you learn specifically that one, you learn specifically the laws of
an אשם *asham* it counts as an אשם *asham*. And that's an
idea that is definitely very much like, you know, embedded in I
think like the traditional mindset, you know, why sometimes like they, you
know, there's a practice just saying the קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot* before for
those who say the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, you know, before the פסוקי
דזמרא *Pesukei d'Zimra*, because by learning the laws of those קרבנות korbanot,
*korbanot*, it's like you offered their קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* and there's even
a יהי רצון *yehi ratzon*, may it be that my saying of
these פסוקים *psukim* and learning of these laws should be as if
I offered. Okay, so that really really emphasizes not the idea of
תורה *Torah* as a separate track, but the קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot* as
the model and the תורה *Torah* of a way of achieving it.
You know, in a way you could say that that's the whole,
you know, a way of thinking about why is there so much
גמרא gemara. *Gemara* on זבחים *Zvachim* and מנחות Menachot *Menachos*, you know,
when something that is not relevant to חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*? Okay, so
you know תורה *Torah* is not just about what's relevant, but part
of this is, you know, building these intellectual worlds through תורה *Torah*
is our substitute of doing it itself. All right, and that is
the כאילו הקריב *k'ilu hikriv*. It's really worth taking a look at
this תוספות *Tosafot* here, this small תוספות *Tosafot*, מיכאל שר גדול *Michael
Sar Gadol*. תוספות *Tosafot* says the following: עומד עליו ומקריב עליו קרבן
korban *omed alav u'makriv alav korban*. מדרשות חלוקין *midrashot chalukin*, there's different
מדרשים *Midrashim* about this idea. יש מי שאומר נשמותיהם של צדיקים הם
*yesh mi she-omer nishmotehem shel tzaddikim hem*. Who's being offered as the
קרבן *korban*? So some say it is the souls of the צדיקים
*tzaddikim*, you know, the צדיקים *tzaddikim* die, their souls are up in
heaven, then they're being like offered again on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* to
God. It's a pretty graphic and to some degree disturbing image, you
know,
in a way, you know, it might work for if particularly, you
know, in the middle from תוספות *Tosafot*'s perspective, the Jews who suffered
martyrdom and were killed and were as if קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*, you
know, the whole word שואה *Shoah*, you know, whole debate about the
use of the term שואה *Shoah* because that word itself means like
a burnt offering, is that really something do we understand it in
that theological lens? So that's one way, you know, that תוספות *Tosafot*
is sort of saying that the souls of the צדיקים *tzaddikim* and
maybe again those that gave up their lives for God, they're offering
their lives to God. ויש מי שאומר *v'yesh mi she-omer*, and some
say כבשים של אש *kvasim shel esh*. No, no, no, let's not
get so graphic or so like personal almost and I would say
theologically challenged. It's, you know, everything is like heavenly, a heavenly מזבח
*mizbe'ach*, a heavenly angel, a heavenly lamb, so it's just the עבודה
*avodah* like we know it. Okay, but still it speaks to its
power, somehow its metaphysical power. והיינו דאמרינן בשמונה עשרה *v'hainu d'amrinan b'Shmoneh
Esrei*, this is really why I wanted to see the תוספות *Tosafot*,
בעבודה *b'avodah*, you know, in the רצה Retzei *Retzei*, ואשי ישראל ותפלתם
מהרה באהבה תקבל ברצון *v'ishei Yisrael u-tfilatam meherah b'ahavah tekabel b'ratzon*. Accept
the אשי ישראל *ishei Yisrael*, the fire offerings of Israel. What are
the fire offerings of Israel? It is this idea. We don't have
a בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* now, but we're saying the רצה retzei
*Retzei*, accept אשי *ishei*, accept the fire offerings. The fire offerings is
the way that מיכאל *Michael* is still offering up fire sacrifices to
God. Okay, you didn't realize you were saying that when every day
you say שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shmoneh Esrei*. ויש אומרים *v'yesh omrim*,
and some say דקאי אדלעיל *d'kai ad'le'il*. No, no, no, ואשי ישראל
*v'ishei Yisrael* doesn't go on ואשי ישראל ותפלתם תקבל ברצון *v'ishei Yisrael
u-tfilatam tekabel b'ratzon*, accept with love, accept the אשי ישראל *ishei Yisrael*,
the fire offerings. It goes on the previous sentence, השב את et
העבודה לדביר ביתך ואשי ישראל *hashev et ha-avodah lidvir beitecha v'ishei Yisrael*.
Restore the worship to your holy, you know, house and the אשי
ישראל *ishei Yisrael*. So again תוספות *Tosafot* doesn't exactly explain what אשי
ישראל *ishei Yisrael* here means. Some say it means actually in this
reading it means and the Jewish people, restore the Jewish like אנשי
ישראל *anshei Yisrael*, restore the Jewish people to your house. Okay, so
it's not talking or even if it means fire offerings, it's not
saying accept our fire offerings, we're not making any fire offerings now,
it's restore our fire offerings. Okay, so that line that we say
every day in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei, *Shmoneh Esrei*, what are these
אשי ישראל *ishei Yisrael*, is it something that we want God to
accept now that somehow is still happening up in heaven, or is
it that we want God to restore them or maybe we want
God to restore the Jewish people, maybe that's what the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* means. I do want to use that as an opportunity to
mention, you know, something that is quite striking in this whole discussion
of Torah as it counts as the
קרבנות, korbanot, תפילה tefillah is כנגד keneged the קרבנות, korbanot with all
that idea, the whole discussion in ברכות Berachot that the תפילה tefillah
is כנגד keneged the קרבנות, korbanot three prayers, תמיד tamid of the
morning, תמיד tamid of the late afternoon.
It is striking, striking that nowhere in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is
there any explicit mention of קרבנות, korbanot? right? Even when you get
to the רצה and the word רצה like לרצות lirtzot is all
about קרבנות, korbanot, it's all it's described as the ברכה bracha of
the עבודה, it doesn't mention the word קרבן never appears, you can
read that פסוק pasuk and not know that we're talking about
קרבנות. korbanot, The emphasis is תפילתם תקבל ברצון, tefillatam tekabel beratzon, accept
our prayer,
and אישי ישראל Ishei Yisrael as we see is very vague, what
does it mean? Jewish people, fire offerings, what fire offerings? So it's
quite remarkable that חז"ל did not mention קרבנות korbanot. anywhere in שמונה
עשרה, and I think the reason is, and similar to the discussion
of Torah, that if you see that what we're doing now is
only a substitute, our תפילה tefillah is a substitute for קרבנות, korbanot.
our Torah is a substitute for קרבנות, korbanot that does
not allow us to feel that we are living a full life
of
עבודת השם. avodat Hashem. Better to say like רבא Rava says, if
you're doing Torah you don't need קרבנות. תפילה tefillah is different than
קרבנות, maybe תפילה tefillah is just as acceptable as קרבנות, that is
a statement that appears in the name of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai that it is not כנגד keneged קרבנות but
it is equivalent or maybe even better. Actually, the פסוק pasuk that
we open שמונה עשרה with, השם שפתי תפתח ופי יגיד תהלתך, Hashem
sefatai tiftach u-fi yagid tehilatecha, the immediate next פסוק pasuk in תהלים
Tehillim says something
like כי לא תחפוץ זבח ואתנה עולה לא תרצה. זבחי אלקים רוח
נדבה, ki lo tachpotz zevach ve-ettenah olah lo tirtzeh. Zivchei Elokim ruach
nedava, what God wants is
the generous spirit, a לב נשבר ונדכה אלקים לא תבזה, lev nishbar
venidkeh Elokim lo tivzeh, God does not despise a broken heart. So,
quite significant, is it about כנגד keneged קרבנות or is it about
a track completely unrelated to קרבנות?
Okay, last משנה mishna and last גמרא. gemara Here's what משנה mishna
says. So we've been dealing with this whole פרק perek about when
you say I'm giving X, I'm giving a sheep, I'm giving an
ox, do you mean a big one, do you mean a small
one, what's the minimum, what's the, what exactly, how much you mean
when you dedicate something. So here the משנה mishna says, a beautiful
way of ending this מסכת, masechet, נאמר בעולת בהמה, nemar be-olat behemah,
it says by the עולה olah of a
בהמה, behemah, אישי ריח ניחוח, ishei rei'ach nicho'ach, a fire offering, there
you go your אישי ishei again, אישי ישראל. Ishei Yisrael. So a
burnt offering, a pleasing scent, ובעולת עוף אישי ריח ניחוח, uve-olat of
ishei rei'ach nicho'ach, and the same by a bird burnt offering,
ובמנחה אישי ריח ניחוח, uve-mincha ishei rei'ach nicho'ach, a burnt offering, and
a מנחה mincha is a type of, even though it's not the
full thing, it's right there after the עולה olah and it's a
type of a free-will sacrifice for somebody who can't afford an animal
עולה. olah. Okay,
לומר לך, lomar lecha, to tell you, אחד המרבה ואחד הממעיט, echad
hamarbeh ve-echad hamam'it, famous line, whether it is one who does a
lot or one who does a little, ובלבד שיכוין לבו לשמים, u-vilvad
she-yechaven libo lashamayim, all of them are equally
ריח ניחוח להשם, rei'ach nicho'ach l'Hashem, what matters is your pure intent.
Okay, אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi Zeira, so said רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira in the גמרא now, מה קרא, mah kra, what's the פסוק
pasuk where we see this idea other than the very פסוק pasuk
that's in the, the equal terms that the משנה mishna mentions, where's
a פסוק pasuk that states explicitly or more explicitly this idea that
אחד המרבה ואחד הממעיט? echad hamarbeh ve-echad hamam'it? So it says, quoting
a פסוק pasuk from קהלת, Kohelet, מתוקה שנת העובד אם מעט ואם
הרבה, metuka shenat ha-oved im meat ve-im harbeh, the sleep of the
worker is
sweet whether a lot or a little. So again, what does that
mean? So in this context, we're explaining it, the one who brings
a קרבן and goes home to sleep, his sleep is just as
sweet and his reward
is just as good, whether he brought a lot or a little,
יאכל yochal either way he shall eat, get equal reward. רב אדא
בר אהבה אמר מהכא, Rav Adda bar Ahava amar me-hacha, רב אדא
בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava says from here, ברבות הטובה רבו
אוכליה, birbot hatova rabu ochleha, again from משלי, Mishlei, ברבות הטובה רבו
אוכליה, birbot hatova rabu ochleha, with the increase in the goodness you've
increased those who eat it, if you bring more sacrifices more כהנים
kohanim eat it, ומה כשרון לבעליה כי אם ראות עיניו, uma kishron
livalah ki im re'ot einav, but what benefit is it to the
owner, meaning to God, right? And the end of the פסוק pasuk
is כי אם ראות עיניו, ki im re'ot einav, but what the
owner sees. So for God, very nice, you fed the כהנים, kohanim,
but as far as God is concerned, it is what God can
see which is what your motivation was, the purity of your spirit.
Okay, תניא אמר רבי שמעון בן עזאי, Tanya amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Azzai, said רבי שמעון בן עזאי, Rabbi Shimon ben Azzai, בוא ראה
מה כתיב בפרשת קרבנות, bo re'eh mah ketiv be-parshat korbanot, see what
it says by the קרבנות, שלא נאמר בהן, she-lo nemar ba-hen, now
it's sort of wrapping up and dealing with some theological... theological issue
about the קרבנות, we'll have some other reflections. שלא shelo נאמר ne'emar
בהן bahen לא lo אל El ולא velo אלוהים. Elokim. Throughout the
whole part of ויקרא Vayikra it doesn't say אל El and it
doesn't say אלוהים, Elokim, those names of God, אלא ella השם, Hashem,
it's י"ק ו"ק. Yud Kay Vav Kay. שלא shelo ליתן liten פתחון
פה pitchon peh לבעלים laba'alim לחלוק, lachlok, that nobody should have no
antagonist should have an opening to challenge, meaning to say that it's
referring to bringing it
to pagan gods, which אל El and אלוהים Elokim could refer to,
understanding that we are referring only to
השם. Hashem. ונאמר vene'emar בשור beshor הגס, hagas, it says by a
big ox, אשה ishe ריח rei'ach ניחוח, nicho'ach, ובעוף uv'of הדק, hadak,
and by a small bird, אשה ishe ריח rei'ach ניחוח, nicho'ach, ובמנחה
uv'minchah אשה ishe ריח rei'ach ניחוח, nicho'ach, למה לך, lamah lach, this
is what was in the משנה, Mishnah, אחד echad המרבה hamarbeh ואחד
ve'echad הממעיט hamam'it ובלבד uvildav שיכוון sheyechaven לבו libo לשמים, lashamayim, whether
a lot or a little, if what matters is that you have
the right intent.
ושמא veshema תאמר tomar לאכילה la'achilah הוא hu צריך, tzarich, now we're
really going to get to an important theological statement. Why does God
ask for the sacrifices? Maybe he needs them to consume it, like
לחם lechem אלוהיו, Elokav, the bread of God, he smells it, אשה
ishe ריח rei'ach ניחוח, nicho'ach, very anthropomorphic language. תלמוד talmud לומר, lomar,
no, the פסוק pasuk is clear, אם im ארעב ervav לא lo
אומר omar לך, lach, were I to ever be hungry I would
not tell you, כי ki לי li תבל tevel ומלואה, umlo'ah, I
have the whole world, I don't need you to feed me. Obviously
God doesn't need to be fed at all, but even if he
would, this is not going to do it. ונאמר vene'emar כי ki
לי li כל kol חיתו chayto יער, yaar, for
mine is all of the animals of the forest, בהמות behemot בהררי
beharere אלף, eleph, the animals on the thousands of mountains, ידעתי yadati
כל kol עוף oph הרים, harim, I know all of the birds
of the mountains, וזיז veziz שדי saday עמדי, imadi, and the wild
animals of the field are with me. I don't need you to
bring me קרבנות. This is not the pagan idea of the gods
are hungry and need to be fed. האוכל haochal בשר besar אבירים
abirim ודם v'dam עתודים atudim אשתה, eshteh, do I eat the meat
of the mighty beasts and do I drink their blood? לא lo
אמרתי amarti עליכם aleichem זבחו zivchu כדי, kedei, now we're going to
explain what effectively God is saying. So okay, if I don't need
it to eat from it, why am I telling you to bring
sacrifices? Good question. What's the idea of sacrifices? So לא lo אמרתי
amarti עליכם aleichem זבחו zivchu כדי kedei שתאמר shetomar אעשה e'eseh רצונו
retzono ויעשה veya'aseh רצוני. retzoni. I didn't say to you bring sacrifices
so you can say oh, I did what God wanted now God
will do what I want. God wants this, God needs this from
me and I've given God what God wants so now I'm going
to get something that I want. No. לא lo לרצוני lirtzoni אתם
atem זובחים, zovchim, it's not for my sake, I don't need your
קרבנות. אלא ella לרצונכם lirtzonchem אתם atem זובחים, zovchim, it's for your
sake. By you doing
מצוות, mitzvot, that ultimately is for your benefit. You're not doing me
any favors. I'm giving you this so that that will be of
benefit for you in the doing of
מצוות. mitzvot. שנאמר shenemar לרצונכם lirtzonchem תזבחו, tizbachu, for your sake offer
it, not for
mine. What this suggests is that it's certainly not far to jump
from here to רמב"ם's Rambam idea, which is
that sacrifices are a concession to the human need to feel a
way of more physically connecting to God. I mean רמב"ם Rambam actually
says there was it was a pagan way of believing that the
God or the gods were worshipped so the תורה had to wean
us away from it and use it to serve God, but I
would sort of more to say the human need for a more
embodied connection, I'm doing it for your sake, not for my sake.
I think that is one way of reading it certainly, but minimally
of course what it is saying is I don't need it, you're
not doing me any favors, this is a מצווה mitzvah for you.
Last point, now we return after those really interesting theological reflections, we
return to the last point about
הלכה. halacha. דבר אחר davar acher לרצונכם lirtzonchem תזבחו, tizbachu, לרצונכם lirtzonchem
זבחו, zivchu, for your will, your desire, לדעתכם lada'atchem זבחו, zivchu, means
with your intentionality. כידבעי kideba'i מיניה minei שמואל Shmuel מרב הונא, meRephuna,
like שמואל Shmuel asked רב הונא. Rephuna. מניין minayin למתעסק lemitasek בקדשים
bekodashim שהוא shehu פסול, pasul, how do you know that if somebody
is just שוחט shechting sacrifices without being aware that they're שוחט shechting
sacrifices, מתעסק, mitasek, like almost in passing, that it's
invalid? שנאמר shenemar ושחט veshachat את בן הבקר, ben habakar, you should
slaughter the calf, שתהא shetehei שחיטה shechitah לשם leshem בן בקר, ben
bakar, it should be recognizing that this is a calf and also
that this is a
sacrifice. אמר ליה, amar lo, so he said back to him, זו
zu בידינו beyadeinu היא, hi, we obviously we know that, but that
there's a מצווה mitzvah to do it with that
intentionality. לעכב bela'akev מניין, minayin, how do you know that without that
it actually it's
invalid? תלמוד talmud לומר lomar לרצונכם lirtzonchem תזבחו. tizbachu. The extra פסוק
for your desire, meaning your intention, לדעתכם lada'atchem זבחו, zivchu, only with
if you're intending. As a שחיטה shechita for sacrifice does count and
otherwise it does not count. Interesting to be ending מנחות Menachot. about
שחט-ing shechting and not on the idea of a מנחה, mincha, but
very nice to have these final theological reflections of the purpose of
sacrifice and the relationship of תורה to קרבנות as well.
הדרן עלך עשרון, Hadran alach Isaron, הדרן עלך עשרון, Hadran alach Isaron,
וסליקא לך מסכת מנחות. u'slika lach masechet Menachot. יישר כח, Yashar koach,
יישר כח yashar koach to everybody who has just now completed learning
מנחות.